Guide to the Clelia D. Mosher Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Clelia D. Mosher Papers
1886-1938
SC0011
Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1863-1940
4.75 Linear feet (6 boxes)
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
The Clelia Mosher Papers were given to the Stanford University Libraries by the Mosher estate following Dr. Mosher's death in 1940. The papers were stored but not arranged until the creation of the University Archives in 1965.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Alternative Formats
Volume X, The Mosher Sex Survey is available on microfilm.
Separated Materials
Some photographs of Clelia Mosher, both formal and informal, and of women students in exercise studies by Mosher were transferred to the Stanford Historical Photograph Collection (SC1071).
Christmas cards from Herbert Hoover were transferred to the Hoover Institution Archives.
Bibliography
Publications based on use of this collection include:
Degler, Carl. "What ought to be and what was: women's sexuality in the 19th century," American Historical Review 79:5 (1974) 1474-1490.
Degler, Carl. "A 'dream' discovery: the Mosher survey," Imprint 3:2 (Oct. 1977).
Jacobs, Kathryn Allamong. "Clelia Duel Mosher," Johns Hopkins Magazine (June 1979).
The Mosher Survey: sexual attitudes of 45 Victorian women. Edited by James Mahoon and Christine Wenberg, with an introduction by Carl Degler. New York: Arno Press, 1980.
Biographical Note:
Clelia Duel Mosher, the daughter of Cornelius Duel Mosher, M.D. and Sarah Burritt Mosher, was born on December 16, 1863 in Albany, New York. She graduated from Wellesley College in 1891, and spent the next year studying at both Cornell University and the University of Wisconsin. She then attended Stanford University, receiving an A.B. in zoology in 1893 and a masters in physiology in 1894. She received her M.D. from Johns Hopkins University in 1900.
Dr. Mosher returned to Palo Alto to set up practice as a physician. She joined the Stanford faculty as a professor of personal hygiene in 1910, retiring as Professor emeritus in 1929. Interested particularly in women's health, she carried out her research and writing interests both as a physician and faculty member in the Department of Physical Hygiene, the linear ancestor of Stanford's Department of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation.
Mosher was a fellow in the American Medical Association (1906-1936) and in the American Association for Advancement of Science. She was also a member of Phi Beta Kappa, Sigma Xi, and Kappa Alpha Theta. An avid genealogist, she was a member of the Daughters of the American Revolution.
Between 1901 and 1929, Mosher published twenty-one books, including four "War Sketches" which appeared in the Medical Woman's Journal, 1921. She died in Palo Alto in 1940.
Scope and Contents Note:
The collection contains primarily correspondence, writings (published and unpublished), diaries, and biographical and genealogical material spanning the years 1886 to 1938. Correspondents include Ray Lyman Wilbur, William H. Welch (President of Johns Hopkins), David Starr Jordan, and Havelock Ellis.
Six bound volumes of her notes, reports, and charts, Hygiene and Physiology of Women, can be found in box 3. Volume "X" of this series, known as the Mosher Sex Survey, has been republished as
The Mosher Survey: Sexual Attitudes of 45 Victorian Women (edited by James Mahood and Christine Wenberg. New York: Arno Press, 1980, 469 pp.).
Boxes 3 and 4 also include extensive biographical and genealogical material, including photographs.
Access Terms
Coolidge, Mary Roberts,, 1860-1945.; Ellis, Havelock,, 1859-1939.; Jordan, David Starr,, 1851-1931.; Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1863-1940; Stanford University. Department of Physical Hygiene. -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Welch, William H.; Wilbur, Ray L., (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949; Sex customs--History.--United States; Women--Health and hygiene--United States.; Women--Sexual behavior--History.
Collection Contents
- Publications and letters (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Health and the Woman Movement, (New York National Board, YWCA), 1916 Jan; 47 page(s)
  - Conference pamphlet, ( Mosher, Clelia Duel spoke), 1915 May
  - The Relation of Health to the Woman Movement, final copy.
  - Letter: To Dr. Mosher from Margaret Johnson, University of Wisconsin, 1915 Jul 15
  - Dr. Mosher to Dr. Johnson, 1915 Jul 20
  - Telegram: To Dr. Mosher from Elva L. Sly, 1915 Jul 21
  - Dr. Mosher to Elva L. Sly, 1915 Jul 21
  - Dr. Mosher to Elva L. Sly, 1915 Aug 6
  - Letter: To Dr. Mosher from Dr. Anna L. Brown, 1915 Aug 9
  - Dr. Mosher to Helen Thoburn, 1915 Aug 10
  - To Dr. Mosher from Thorvald Solberg, 1915 Aug 10
  - To Dr. Mosher from Elva L. Sly, 1915 Aug 11
  - To Dr. Mosher from Anna L. Brown, 1915 Sep 15
- Xerox copy of "the Relation of Health to the Woman Movement" (Box 1, Folder 1a)
- Letters and manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Typhoid Fly Problem and Civic Fly Campaigns", 20 page(s)
  - Oxford. Concerning Scarlet Fever Epidemic and Carmel-Postcard-Dr Mosher, 1906 Feb 17
  - Letter: To Dr. Mosher from Ermina R. Stillman, 1906 May 9
  - To Dr. Mosher from ?, 1906 May 5
  - To Dr. Mosher from Barbara H. Alden, 1906 May 22
  - To Dr. Mosher from ? Pierce, 1906 May 17, 24, 29
  - To Dr. Mosher from Charles C. Hill, 1906 Jun 5
  - Copy of letter from Mosher to Mr. Hill, 1906 Jun 8
  - To Dr. Mosher from Dr. Hill, 1906 Jun 12
  - To Dr. Mosher from Bessie M. Ashlaw, 1906 Jun 18
  - Dr. Mosher to Mr. Devendorff, 1906 Jun 21
  - To Dr. Mosher from Ruth Beveridge, undated
  - Dr. Mosher to Ruth Beveridge, on back., 1906 Jul 31
  - Notes: concerning Virginia Newhall, Frances Beveridge, Donald Clampett, Lillian Devendorff, Bessie Ashton, Leanna Davis
  - List of children taken ill.
  - Letter: To Dr. Mosher from Mrs. E.W. Newhall, 1906 Jun 7
  - "Another Method of Avoiding the Public Drinking Cup", 2 pages with example.
- Drafts (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "A Study of the Respiratory Movements in Women,", 1901
    First draft, 12 pages. Second draft, missing page 1, 10 pages
  - "Age Groups of College Women."
    12 pages notes and drafts, and calculations.
- Articles and notes on height, feet and gait in women (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chart - Relation of Change in Fashion to Height and Periodic Disability of Women.
  - "Some of the Causal Factors in the Increased Height of College Women," (1891-1921). Second and Third Note, (Reprint from The Medical Women's Journal, November, 1921.)
  - "A Perfect Shoe for a Perfect Foot," Harriet Wilde.
  - "The Angle of Gait in Women," Sadie D. Patek, American Journal of Physical Anthropology, July- September, 1926., 17 page(s)
  - Newsclipping - "Who Invented Shoes?", Hester Bronson Copper.
  - "A Case of Onychrogryposis," Clelia D. Mosher, A.M., M.D., Reprint from The Woman's Medical Journal, November 1910, 7 pages.
  - "Functional Periodicity in Women and Some of the Modifying Factors," Reprint from The California State Journal of Medicine, Jan-February, 1911, 1923
  - "A Physiologic Treatment of Congestive Dysmenorrhea and Kindred Disorders Associated with the Menstrual Function." 15 pages.
  - Note to self: concerning feet, gait, etc. 3 pages., 1927 Nov 18
- Articles and letters on posture (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Public Health Reports, 1927 May 6
  - A Study of Literature Relating to Posture., 29 page(s)
  - "A Resume, with Comments, of the Available Literature Relating to Posture," Louis Schwartz.
  - "Habits of Posture: A Cause of Deformity and Displacement of the Uterus," Eliza Mosher, M.D., 1893 Nov; 16 page(s)
  - "Faulty Habits of Posture, A Cause of Enteroptosis," Eliza Mosher, M.D., 1914 May; 15 page(s)
  - "The Care of the Abdomen in Infancy and Childhood," Eliza Mosher, M.D., 1914 Dec; 13 page(s)
  - "The Etiology and Diagnosis of Chronic Intestinal Stasis," Eliza Mosher, M.D., 1914 Jan; 8 page(s)
  - "Results of Research on Conditions Affecting Posture," Henry Ling Taylor, 1916 Jun
  - "A Combined Medical and Postural Examination of 746 Young Adults," Lloyd T. Brown, M.D., 1917 Nov
  - The Schematograph - 2 pamphlets describing the Mosher-Lesley Schematograph.
  - "The Schematogram - A New Method of Graphically Recording Posture and Changes in the Contour of the Body," Clelia D. Mosher, 1915 Feb; 8 page(s)
  - Letter: To the Surgeon General from Louis Schwartz, concerning Schematograph., 1928 Jun 4
  - To Dr. Mosher from Louis Schwartz, 1928 Jun 4
  - To Dr. Mosher from R.C. Williams, Assistant Surgeon General, 1928 Jun 7
  - Imitations of the Schematograph - newspaper clippings, 1919 Jul 13
- Correspondence and miscellaneous papers (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Library of Congress Copyright Office - steps to insure copyright.
  - Receipt.
  - Application - Daughters of the American Revolution.
  - Memorandum of Florist business, carried on by Mosher, Clelia Duel in New York, 1888-1889; 1 page(s)
  - "The Tale of Psi's Kite" - publication including article on Dr. Mosher, 1936 Mar
  - Letter and application from Who's Who of American Physicians.
  - Bert,Paul to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1919 Jan 12
  - Postcard E. Homer Bois ? to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1922 Dec 30
  - Ellis, Havelock to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1901 Sep 28, 1921 May 6
  - A. Marion Gammon to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1914 Jun 8
  - Grace Margaret Gneld to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1920 Aug 6
  - Olivia James (Mrs. Henry James) to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1919 Feb 17
  - Vernon Kellogg to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1921 Mar 16
  - Ira S. Lillick to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1935 Sep 23
  - Mary Riggs Noble, M.D. to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1932 Sep 30
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Mary Riggs Noble, 1932 Oct 10
  - Helen W. Peckleane? to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1924 Mar 3
  - Ruth to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1924 Mar 28
  - Lucy M. Salmon to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1911 Apr 26
  - Milicent W. Shinn to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1896 Mar 24
  - Jane Snyder to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1929 Jun 16
  - Ray Lyman Wilbur to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1938 Dec 16
  - Edith Williams to Mosher, Clelia Duel, undated
  - Letter J unsigned., 1920 Jan
  - Letter of Introduction: A.W. Edwards to Mrs. Thompson, undated
  - Letter of Introduction: Gertrude E. Knox to Dr. Patrick, 1924 Mar 21
  - Letter of Introduction: Gertrude E. Knox to John Randolphe, 1924 Mar 21
  - William H. Welch (Johns Hopkins University) to Mr. Ball, undated
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Dr. Kate Campbell Mead, 1932 Oct 10
  - Memo: Mosher, Clelia Duel to Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1919 May 12
  - Memo: Mosher, Clelia Duel to Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1923 Apr 19
  - Memo: Mosher, Clelia Duel to Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1923 Apr 29; 2 pages, 2 copies of first page.
  - Memo: Mosher, Clelia Duel to Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1927 Jan 3
  - Woman's Club - talk on Mosher, Clelia Duel's war experiences.
  - Information sheet re: David Starr Jordan Fund.
  - Expense Sheet, 1892 Jun 4
- Article and letters on drinking water (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Drink More Water and Keep Well", Clelia Duel Mosher, A.M., M.D.
  - Letter to Edward Bok, Ladies Home Journal, submitting article., 1911 Apr 21
  - Examples of folding paper cups.
  - Rejection from Ladies Home Journal., 1911 May 5
  - List of Companies - Sanitary Drinking Fountains.
- Articles (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A Mess of Pottage, 2 pages handwritten and 2 pages typed.
  - A War Produce - Who Pays?, 16 pages (oddly numbered)
  - Earthly Immortality, 12 page(s)
  - The Making of a Misfit, 13 page(s)
  - Gilding the Lily, 5 page(s)
  - 24 Hours in a Day, 9 page(s)
  - It Might Be True, It Might Have Happened, 7 page(s)
  - Sketches and Notes, 29 page(s)
  - Newspaper clipping.
- Articles and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Spring Song, by M.C. Deville (Clelia Mosher), 7 page(s)
  - Notes, 1 page(s)
  - All in a Day's Work, printed pamphlet, 4 pages; second copy, 5 pages typed.
  - Again in the Running, 7 page(s)
  - When Lillie Was Taken, 8 page(s)
  - Madame, 5 page(s)
  - Presque Tours Les Enfants du Pays, 13 page(s)
  - As Seen By a Doctor, 3 pages as introduction to collection of stories above.
  - Correspondence: Cousin Eliza to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1921 May 26
  - Correspondence: Jordan, David Starr to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1921 Sep 17
  - Correspondence: Wilbur, Ray Lyman to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 31-May-21
- Diaries and other papers (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1926 Apr 16
  - Notes on medical problems and issues, personal thoughts
    54 pages
  - 1919 Mar 15, 1 page(s)
  - 1921 Jan 30
    4 pages
  - 1926 Jun 6, 2 page(s)
  - 1928 May 16, 1 page(s)
  - 1926 May 26, Oct 27, 6 page(s)
  - 1906 Jul 19, 1 page(s)
  - 1930 May 13, 1 page(s)
  - 1932 Feb 14, 1 page(s)
  - 1931 Aug 5, 1 page(s)
  - Jan, 1 page(s)
  - 1926 Dec 20, 1 page(s)
  - 1933 Dec 24-1934 Jan 21, 2 page(s)
  - undated, 17 page(s)
  - Diary
    15 pages
- Biographical materials (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel- The Questioner (biographical sketch), 23 page(s)
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel M.D. - Publications, 1901-1920; 2pp.
  - Coolidge, Mary Roberts to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1933 Jul 15
  - Biographical Information, brief
  - Newsclippings on Clelia Mosher's death - Palo Alto Times, 1940 Dec 23
  - Biographical Information, 1 page(s)
  - Revisions on biography, 2 page(s)
  - Comments on biography by Mary R. Coolidge, 2 pages handwritten, 1 page typed.
  - Theme written by Mosher, Clelia Duel while at Wellesley College, 5 pages handwritten, 2 pages typed.
  - Comments on Theme and C.D. Mosher's composition training, 6 pages handwritten, 4 pages typed.
  - Information on Mosher, Clelia Duel's education, 2 page(s)
  - Memorial to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 3 page(s)
- Materials on Mosher's medical studies (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Contribution to the Study of the Inquiry of Gall Stones in the United States," Mosher, Clelia Duel. Report of the Johns Hopkins Medical Society Meeting, March 4, 1901. From Maryland Medical Journal, 1901 May; 5 page(s)
  - Journal article - "The Health of Women Wage Earners," 1 page, Mosher, Clelia Duel cited in article.
  - Newsclippings and notes on Mosher, Clelia Duel's work.
  - Letter: S.M. Croonquist to Mosher, Clelia Duel and attached newsclipping.
  - Notes, 3 page(s)
  - Newsclippings on Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1920 Dec 15, 1933 Oct 18
  - Journal article re: Mosher, Clelia Duel's work - The Literary Digest, 1923 Sep 29
  - Article including Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1929 Jul
- Correspondence and miscellaneous papers (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letter: Havelock Ellis to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1901 Sep 28
  - Registered Mail slip and Return Receipt.
  - Receipt for payment of typing work, 1902 Dec 13
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Mrs. E.H. Richards, (note at bottom)., 1902 Dec 13
  - Notes - Blood Pressure Studies, 1 page(s)
  - Office of the Dean, Johns Hopkins University, Medical Department to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1903 Feb 24
  - Pertaining to Carnegie Grant:
    - David Starr Jordan to Secretary of Carnegie Institute, 1905 May 22
    - N.M. Gilbert? to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1905 Jun 10
    - Mary Roberts Smith to Trustees of Carnegie Institute, 1905 Sep 20
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Honorable W.W. Morrow.
    - William W. Morrow to Dr. Robert J. Woodward, 1905 Sep 25
    - Willaim W. Morrow to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1905 Sep 26
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to William W. Morrow, 1905 Sep 29
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Charles D. Walcott, 1905 Sep 29
    - Receipt from Wells Fargo & Co. Express, 1905 Sep 28
    - G. Stanley Hall to Mosher, Clelia Duel, and 2 copies., 1905 Oct 2
    - N.M. Gilbert to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1905 Oct 3
    - Howard A. Kelly to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1905 Oct 5
    - N.M. Gilbert to Howard A. Kelly, 1905 Oct 6
    - W.H. Howell to Mosher, Clelia Duel, and copy., 1905 Oct 7
    - N.M. Gilbert to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1905 Oct 7
    - John Henry Comstock to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 10-Oct-05
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Dr. Charles D. Walcott, 11-Oct-05
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Dr. William H. Howell, 12-Oct-05
    - N.M. Gilbert to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 13-Oct-05
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Professor Comstock, 16-Oct-05
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Dr. Howard A. Kelly, 1905 Oct 16
    - N.M. Gilbert to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1905 Oct 17
    - N.M. Gilbert to C.H. Gilbert, 1905 Oct 25
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Dr. William H. Welch, 1906 Jan 9
    - R.S. Woodward to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1906 Jan 15
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Hon. Charles W. Walcott, 1906 Jan 9
    - Postal Receipt, 1906 Jan 9
    - R.S. Woodward to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 25-Jan-06
    - David Starr Jordan to Florence M. Cushing, 1909 Jan 9
    - D. Charles Gardner to Florence M. Cushing, 1909 Jan 12
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Mrs. N.P. Hallowell, 1909 Jan 23
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Florence M. Cushing, January 23, 1909, 1909 Jan 24
    - Sarah Hallowell to Mosher, Clelia Duel, reverse side: Mosher, Clelia Duel to Mrs. N.P. Hallowell, 1909 Jan 28, Feb 3
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Dr. Emily Lewi, 1910 Jan 17
    - Mrs. Dane Coolidge to Dr. Emily Lewi, 1910 Jan 19
    - Sarah Hallowell to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1909 Mar 3
    - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Mrs. N.P. Hallowell, 1909 Mar 9
    - Sarah Hallowell to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1909 Mar 20
  - Sheet headed Enclosures, 1 page(s)
  - Sheet headed Previous Record (Academic), 1 page(s)
  - Outline of A Study of Menstruation, 4 pages, second copy, 3 pages.
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Dr. Emily Lewi, 1910 Jan 18
  - Normal Menstruation and the Factors Which May Modify It, 1 page(s)
  - Notes, 3 page(s)
  - Information on Fellowship of the Woman's Education Association, 1 page(s)
  - Information on Alice Freeman Palmer Memorial Fellowship, 1 page(s)
  - Typed pages re: normal menstruation, 2 page(s)
  - Mary Roberts Coolidge to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1910 Jan 20
  - List of persons written to for recommendations.
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel to C.D. Gilbert, undated
  - Information sheet on Mary Putnam Jacobi Fellowship, 1 page(s)
  - Personal Hygiene for Women, book cover.
  - J.H. Comstock re: Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1891 Aug 29
  - Sarah Woodman Paul re: Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1891 Sep 7
  - Sarah Woodman Paul to Secretary of Wisconsin University, 1891 Sep 7
  - Certification of Mosher, Clelia Duel's dismission from Wellesley, 1891 Sep 7
  - Sheet on Mosher, Clelia Duel's German education
  - Certification of Mosher, Clelia Duel's studies, 1892 Jun 15
  - Certification of honorable dismissal from University of Wisconsin, 1892 Jun 17
  - Certification of Admission to Stanford, 1892 Jul 7
  - Ellen Hayes to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1894 Oct 30
  - C.F. Hodges re: Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1896 Jan 10; 2 copies.
  - C.H. Gilbert re: Mosher, Clelia Duel, and copy., 1896 Apr 16
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel to registrar of Johns Hopkins University, 1896 Apr 11
  - O.P. Jenkins re: Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1896 Apr 22; 3 copies.
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Dr. William H. Welch, 1896 Jun 30
  - Photograph Johns Hopkins University.
  - Photograph Dr. William H. Welch and President Herbert Hoover.
  - Note Jim Flexus (?) to Dr. Herdin, undated
  - William Welch to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1896 May 5, Jul 13, Aug 12
  - Steward W. Young re: Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1896 Jul 23
  - D.W. Murphy re: Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1896 Jul 27
  - Note signed H.A. Kelly regarding employment of Mosher, Clelia Duel.
  - W.H. Howell to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1900 Jun 11
  - Henry M. Hurd to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1900 Jun 27
  - Frederick Burk to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1901 Feb 19
  - Mosher, Clelia Duel to Frederick Burk, undated
  - Frederick Burk to Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1901 Mar 11, Apr 4
  - Certification of Credentials - Stanford, 1937 Feb 27
- Wellesley College items (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Envelope containing small bound book from Wellesley pertaining to college requirements.
  - Book of College Courses.
- Diplomas and miscellaneous items (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Honorary Degree Mills
  - Sigma XI Award
  - Comrades in Zeal, by David Starr Jordan.
- Bound Diaries, 1917, 1922, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Studies and publications (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Possistoreme Stouti (Hag Fish) From Monterey Bay"
  - "A Study of the Circulatory System, in the Zoological Laboratory of the Leland Stanford Junior University", 1892-1893
  - Bound volume, publications by Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1901-1929
- Hygiene and Physiology of Women (Box 3)
  Bound volumes I, III, IV, V, VI, and X. Includes reports, charts, papers, and correspondence of Dr. Mosher. Volume X is Mosher's "sex survey."
- The Moshers, 1794-1937, and Related Families, Vol. II: Christopher Mosher, His Descendants and Related Families (Box 3)
  This bound genealogy includes history of related persons, photographs, certificates and some correspondence, clips and sketches.
- Biography, by Clelia Duel Mosher; bound volumes (Box 4)
  - I. Women - includes articles on prominent women, women soldiers, women candidates for president, etc.
  - II. The Woman Movement - studies and notes.
    contains Susan B. Anthony, Cady Stanton, and other suffragettes.
    Anthony, Susan B., (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906.; Astell, Mary, 1668-1731.; Stanton, Elizabeth Cady, 1815-1902.; Wollstonecraft, Mary, 1759-1797.; Woodhull, Victoria C., (Victoria Claflin), 1838-1927.; Feminism--United States.; Women--Suffrage.
  - III. Mary Astell, Part 1: Biographical material. Part 2: Works.
  - IV. Paul Bert - His Family - His Friends - includes clippings, photographs, correspondence.
  - V. Eliza M. Mosher, M.D. - Pioneer Woman Physician, 1896-1928. Includes portrait, characteristics, occupations, letters, memorial, publications.
- Photograph album, Mosher Family (Box 5)
- Publications by Mosher (Box 6)
  - Woman's Physical Freedom, New York: The Woman's Press, 1923
  - "Strength of Women," reprinted from the Proceedings of the International Conference of Women Physicians, 1920
  - "The Height of College Women (Second Note)," reprinted from the Medical Woman's Journal, 1921 Nov
  - "Concerning the Size of Women: Preliminary Note with Special Reference to Height," reprinted from the California State Journal of Medicine, 1921 Feb
  - "The Means to the End," reprinted from the American Physical Education Review, 1925 Dec
  - "The Physical Training of Women in Relation to Functional Periodicity," reprinted from The Woman's Medical Journal, 1915 Apr
  - "A Physiologic Treatment of Congestive Dysmenorrhea and Kindred Disorders Associated with the Menstrual Function," reprinted from the Journal of the American Medical Association, 1914 Apr